创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在 所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了我们生存的限制
beyond the limits of our existence...
这个空间我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
穿梭太空
Streaking through space...
光是宇宙间最快的东西
light is the fastest thing in the universe.
它可以在一秒钟内绕地球7圈
It could circle the Earth seven times in one second.
正是它从遥远的地方来到我们这里
As it reaches us across vast distances...
揭示了宇宙的历史
it reveals the history of the cosmos.
我们可以回眸过去
We're able to look back in time.
光的传播是每秒钟18.6万英里
Light travels at 186,000 miles per second.
其速度是极限
Its speed is an ultimate barrier.
任何东西都无法逾越
Nothing can go faster.
我们从来没有打破过这个速度极限
We have never ever broken the speed limit.
然而这是最终的答案吗?
But is the answer final?
飞船的速度能超过光速吗?
Will spaceships ever speed faster than light?
值得一试吗?
Is it even worth trying?
未经努力就放弃 本身就是放弃
To give up without trying is just giving up.
它触摸不到
It can neither be touched nor felt.
它是巨大影响的抽象量
It is an abstract quantity of immense impact...
是所有物体最核心的运动速度
the rate of motion at the very heart of all existence.
宇宙的根本基石
The fundamental lynchpin of the universe...
我们将其称为《光速》
that we call light speed.
宇宙:光速
在地球上 速度广受欢迎
On planet Earth, where speed is in demand...
最快的人 最快的车 最快的技术
the fastest people, vehicles, and technologies...
仿佛在光速为王的宇宙中爬行
seem to crawl in a cosmos where light speed is king.
光速不仅仅是老大
More than king, the speed of light is the cornerstone...
而且还是构建宇宙的基石
on which the universe is built.
物理学上有句名言
There's a famous saying in physics...
那就是光速不光是好想法 而且还是定律
which is that the speed of light is not just a good idea, it's the law.
光速是宇宙间最重要的
The speed of light is one of the most important speed limits...
速度极限之一
in the entire universe.
光速 每秒18.6万英里
The speed of light, 186,000 miles per second...
简直难以置信
is just incredible.
我的意思是 如果光绕着地球转
I mean, if light traveled in a circle around the Earth...
每秒钟可以转上7圈
it could circle the Earth seven times in one second.
那是个惊人的速度
That's an incredible speed.
这惊人的速度是我们碰到光现象时的
That incredible speed is the first thing we encounter...
立马反应
when confronting the phenomenon of light.
说它快是极大的轻描淡写
To say it is fast is a colossal understatement.
令我惊诧的是 在我手机通话时
It's amazing to me that when I talk on my cell phone...
显然可以跨境与人交流
I can talk to somebody clear across the country...
不会感觉有任何时间滞后
and I'm not really aware of any time lag...
信号从我的手机到信号塔
and that signal is going from my phone to a tower...
传到卫星 再返回 似乎就在刹那间
up to a satellite, back down, and it seems instantaneous.
因此我们确实想当然
So we really take for granted...
认为光速对我们来说几乎是无限的
the speed of light could practically be infinite to us.
南加州大学的物理教授克利福德.约翰逊
Physics professor Clifford Johnson of USC...
是一位狂热的自行车运动员
is an avid bike rider.
围绕着赛道 他思量着努力走完
Circling a track, he considers trying to cover...
同样的18.6万英里 那是光在一秒钟里走过的
the same 186,000 miles that light does in one second.
他会发现 不管怎样 他的工作很适合自己
He'll find, however, that his work will be cut out for him.
光在一秒钟里走过的路程
To travel the distance that light moves in just one second...
我骑车需要22个月
it would take me 22 months on a bike...
每小时骑上12英里 日夜骑行才行
moving at 12 miles an hour, cycling 24 hours a day.
然而光速 相对生命的速度
But the speed of light, in relation to the speed of life...
让我们的世界就按照我们预期的方式运作
makes our world work in just the way we've come to expect.
光速如此之快
One of the beneficial effects for humanity...
给人类带来的一个有益结果
of having the speed of light be as fast as it is...
就是所见即所得
is that what you see is what you get.
光速让日常体验几乎是瞬时而得
Light speed makes everyday experience virtually instantaneous.
电灯一打开 你立马看到光明
When the light bulb goes on, you see it right away.
你周围发生的任何情况立马就注意到了
Anything that happens around you registers immediately.
若干经验清晰地表明
And certain experiences make it crystal clear...
光的传播要快于任何东西 包括声音
that light travels faster than anything else, including sound.
有关光传播速度之快的一个有趣的结果
One interesting consequence of the great speed...
就是你看到闪电
with which light travels is that you see a flash of lightning...
基本上是即时的
essentially instantaneously...
而听到雷声则要稍迟一些
but you hear the thunder only later on.
不过光速也有自己的局限
But light speed has its limits...
一旦处于宇宙这样大的地方
when stacked up to a place as large as the universe.
我们认为光速在人类的尺度上
We think that the speed of light...
是难以想象的快
is unimaginably fast on a human scale.
但是 在天文上 它其实有点慢
However, in astronomical terms, it's actually kind of pokey.
因此讽刺的是 当年阿波罗飞船进入太空后
And so it's ironic that when the Apollo spacecraft blasted into space...
速度达到了惊人的2.5万英里/小时
traveling at what seemed an amazing 25,000 miles per hour...
在与23.6万英里外的
the speed of light proved frustratingly slow...
月球上的宇航员交流时
when it came time to talk to astronauts...
光速被证明慢的让人沮丧
236,000 miles away on the lunar surface.
宇航员登上月球后
So when the astronauts were on the Moon...
人们问尼尔.阿姆斯特朗
and people asked Neil Armstrong...
嘿 尼尔 上面像什么?
"Hey, Neil, what's it like up there?"
一问一答之间
Several seconds went by between the question...
间隔了几秒钟
and Neil Armstrong's answer.
尼尔 这里是休斯顿 通讯检查 完毕
Neil, this is Houston. Radio check, over.
明白 收到 休斯顿 声音清晰
Aye, roger, Houston, loud and clear.
- 收到 - 清晰 休斯顿
- Roger out. - Loud and clear, Houston.
收到
Roger, Buzz.
那几秒钟
And those several seconds...
并不是因为他在思考答案
were not because he was thinking about the answer...
而是因为需要1.3秒钟
but rather because it took 1.3 seconds...
信号才能以光速
for the signal traveling at the speed of light...
从控制中心传送到尼尔那里
to reach Neil from Mission Control...
他同样需要
and another 1.3 seconds for his reply...
1.3秒钟发回电波
using radio waves to come back...
那2.6秒钟与思考毫不相干
and that's 2.6 seconds without even thinking.
好
Okay.
光从地球传送到月球的1.3秒钟
The 1.3 seconds it takes light to travel from the Earth to the Moon...
相对其它天体来说根本算不上什么
is pocket change compared to other celestial bodies.
比如 来自太阳的阳光
Light from the Sun, for instance...
需要8分多点时间才能到达地球
takes more than eight minutes to get to the Earth.
假如此时太阳消失了
lf the Sun were to disappear right now...
假如太阳突然销声匿迹了
if the Sun were to suddenly vanish...
就需要8分钟
it would take eight minutes...
才能让我们感到冲击波
before we would even feel the shockwave...
看到太阳消失后的结果
and see the effects of a disappearing sun.
光速的限制
The limits of light speed...
同样也给地球与遥远飞船之间的沟通
also make communicating with Earth's far-flung spacecraft...
带来特别的挑战
a special challenge.
需要44分钟让信号来回传送给
It takes up to 44 minutes for signals to travel back and forth...
火星探测器
to the probes exploring Mars...
3个多小时 到卡西尼土星探测器
more than three hours to Cassini at Saturn...
超过29小时 到旅行者1号
and over 29 hours to Voyager 1, the most distant of all...
那是现在所到达的太阳系最远的地方
now heading out of the solar system.
不过这些距离在宇宙尺度上是微不足道的
Still, these distances are trivial on a cosmic scale.
我们几乎可以理解地球
We can almost understand the 10 billion miles...
与旅行者号之间的100亿英里
separating Earth from Voyager...
但是接下去呢?
but what's next?
最近的恒星是颗红矮星 叫做比邻星
The nearest star is a red dwarf named Proxima Centauri...
在近25万亿英里外
nearly 25 trillion miles away.
25后面有12个0
That's 25 followed by 12 zeroes.
我通常被问及一个问题 你作为天文学家 怎么能够
I am often asked a question, "How can you, as an astronomer...
真正理解这些庞大的距离
"really comprehend these vast distances...
这些庞大的数字?
" these huge numbers?"
答案是 我不能
And the answer is, l can't.
人的大脑真的折腾不起这么大的数字
The human brain really doesn't wrap itself around numbers that big.
偶尔 我会写出N多个0
Occasionally, I actually write out...
来表示从这里到某个星系的里程
how many zeroes there are in kilometers from here to a galaxy...
只是为了看看那个数字有多大
just to see how huge that number is.
不过现实中 当然啦 作为天文学家
But in reality, of course, as astronomers...
我们会花上一整天来写0
we would be spending all day writing zeroes...
除非找到更好的单位来使用
unless we came up with a better unit to use...
那就是光年
and that's what a light-year is.
一光年约等于6万亿英里
A light-year is approximately 6 trillion miles.
就是光走上一年的距离
It's the distance that light travels in one year.
用光年来描述距离
Using light-years to describe distances...
打开了光速特性的另一个尺度
opens up another dimension of light speed's character.
来看看 天狼星 天上最亮的恒星
Think of it. Sirius, the brightest star in the sky...
在8.6光年外
is 8.6 light-years away.
那就意味着我们所见到的 不是它今天的模样
That means we see it, not as it is today...
而是它8.6年前的模样
but as it was 8.6 years ago.
我们看到的明亮的织女星是25年前的模样
We see the bright star Vega as it was 25 years ago...
红巨星参宿四的模样是500年前的
and the red super giant Betelgeuse as it was 500 years ago.
它是大自然的精美礼物
It's a wonderful gift of nature...
因为它传播需要时间 所以我们就能够回眸过去
that because it takes time to travel, we're able to look back in time.
我们看得越远 回眸的时间也就越早
The further out we look in distance, the further back in time we look.
我们将无法知道我们宇宙的历史是怎么回事
We would have no idea what our cosmic history was...
如果光速稍纵即逝的话
if the speed of light traveled instantaneously.
劳拉.丹妮是著名的
Laura Danly is curator...
洛杉矶格里菲斯天文台台长
of the historic Griffith Observatory in Los Angeles.
由于光能够将我们带到过去
With light's ability to take us into the past...
她汇集了一叠照片
she's assembled a stack of photos...
讲述光速的宇宙快照故事
that tell light speed's story of the universe in snapshots...
把时间倒回其地点
looking back in time to its beginning...
距今130多亿年前
more than 13 billion years ago to the present day.
我汇总成一本
I'm putting together a scrapbook...
我们星系家族史的剪贴本
of the history of our family of galaxies...
我挑选出我们所有能用望远镜看到的星系
and I chose all the galaxies that we can see with our telescopes...
也就是我们望远镜所能看到的最早的情形
as far back as we can see with our telescopes.
剪贴本里每一幅照片 显示了宇宙中的方方面面
Each photo in this album, then, shows something in the universe...
倒转的时光相当于以光年计的距离
with a look-back time equivalent to its distance in light-years.
著名的蟹状星云 6500年前
The famous Crab Nebula, 6,500 years ago...
银河核心 银河系的中心
the Galactic Core, center of the Milky Way...
2.6万年前
26,000 years ago...
仙女座星系 我们的邻居
and the Andromeda galaxy, our next-door neighbor...
250万年前
2.5 million years ago...
但是在宇宙尺度上恍若昨日
but practically yesterday on a cosmic scale.
我喜欢这个星团
I love this cluster.
将近90%的时光倒流
For almost 90 percent of the look-back time...
剪贴本里充满了普通的星系
the album is filled with common galaxies.
普通 没错 但是千奇百怪
Common, yes, but intriguingly diverse.
这两个正发生碰撞
And these two are colliding.
你看到其中一个
You can see one going...
正在穿越另外一个
what appears to be right through the other...
星系的演变方式有好多个版本
and there's a lot of drama in the way galaxies evolve...
这里它们是相互交织在一起
and the way they interact with one another.
这个应该是
So this one would be...
只是约5亿光年外
Oh, well, it's only about 500 million light-years away.
随着丹妮将一幅幅照片放入剪贴本
As Danly places each shot in the album...
一幅更大的照片开始显现
a bigger picture begins to emerge.
成熟的星系俨然成了主角
Adult galaxies have been the main characters...
它们在过去120亿年里千变万化
evolving in all their variety for the past 12 billion years.
但是宇宙也有其童年的照片
But the cosmos also has its childhood photos...
表现出星系在宇宙幼年时的模样
showing galaxies when the universe was a mere toddler.
这些其实是非常有趣的星系
These are actually very interesting galaxies...
距离约110亿年
at about 11 billion light-years away.
这些紧凑的星系...
These compact galaxies are--
相当于两岁 或两岁半的小孩
Represent what might be a 2 or 2 1/2-year-old child...
要知道 还在蹒跚学步
you know, just really learning how to walk.
不过这些星系都有着自己的弟妹
But even these galaxies have their younger brothers and sisters.
这个美轮美奂的照片显示出一个引力透镜
This spectacular shot shows a gravity lens...
一个22亿光年外的星系团
a cluster of galaxies 2.2 billion light-years away...
弯曲了光线 让我们看到了更加遥远的时空
that bends light, allowing us to see much further in space and time.
透镜揭示了有一个星点
The lens reveals a tiny speck...
被确定为我们所能见到的最早的星系之一
identified as one of the earliest galaxies we can see...
它约在130亿年前
as it was 13 billion light-years ago...
当时成长的宇宙正处在婴儿期
still an infant in the evolving universe.
婴儿期的星系
Galaxies, when they were babies...
确实还没有太多的可分辨的特征
really don't have a lot of distinguishable features.
它们好像是模糊的斑点
They're kind of blobs.
它们实际上还没有复杂的结构
They don't really have a lot of structure.
宇宙 总体上 在其生命之初
The universe, as a whole, was something of a blob...
也就是一个斑点
at the beginning of its life, too.
我们所看到的那个时代就是史上第一道光
What we see of that time are the first light waves in history...
现在才到达我们这里
reaching us only now...
在它们闪射后经过了137亿年
13.7 billion years after they flashed into existence.
我们从大爆炸余辉的照片里看到了它们
We see them in the picture of an afterglow from the Big Bang...
它们现在被称为
and they are known today...
宇宙微波背景辐射
as the cosmic microwave background radiation.
The cosmic microwave background radiation...
是我们能看到的最遥远的东西
is the most distant thing we can see.
它在一定意义上是新生儿的出生照
It is, in a sense, the picture of the baby upon delivery.
航天局的全天空照片显示出一抹光晕
NASA's All-Sky Picture reveals a glow...
我们看到它到处都是一样的
that is uniform everywhere we can see...
此时的宇宙就是宇宙诞生后的那一刻
the universe as it was in a cosmic moment after its birth.
然而到了这里 我们的视野嘎然止步
But here, our view comes to a sudden halt.
我们能看到的宇宙是有限的
What we can see of the universe is limited...
并不是因为我们的设备的大小或能力
not by the size or power of our instruments...
而是受制于光速本身的原因
but by the barrier of light speed itself.
宇宙间最快的东西怎么会
How can the fastest thing in the universe...
让我们在无限的宇宙中变成了睁眼瞎的呢?
make us blind to the infinity of space?
掌握了光速是每年6万亿英里
Knowing that light speed is 6 trillion miles per year...
让我们用上了光年 便捷的速记方法
gives us the light-year, a convenient shorthand...
来讨论宇宙中的巨大距离
for talking about the huge distances in the universe.
不过同样重要的是
But it's just as important to understand...
光速每年6万亿英里
that light speed at 6 trillion miles per year...
是一个铁定的常数
is an ironclad constant.
光速非常恒定
The speed of light is so constant...
宇宙实际上改变了一切
that the universe actually changes everything...
而你从没见到过光有其它的速度
so that you never see it going any other speed.
因此光速确实是
So the speed of light really is the measuring stick...
整个宇宙的标尺
of the entire universe.
事实上 恒定的光速
In fact, the constancy of light speed...
变成了测量浩瀚空间距离的
results in an amazing tool for measuring distance...
绝妙工具
in the vastness of space.
这个工具叫做红移
The tool is called red shift.
它发生在星系之间以固定速度移动时
It happens as light between galaxies travels at a fixed speed.
在星系之间的空间膨胀过程中
When the space between the galaxies expands...
光会被拉长
the light racing between them gets stretched...
转变成红色
turning red in color.
光从一个星系到另一个星系
As light goes from one galaxy to another...
比如 从遥远的星系到我们星系
from a distant galaxy to our own, for example...
光会跟着拉长的空间而拉长
that light gets stretched along with the stretching of space...
这从本质上造成了波长短的光
and that causes intrinsically short-wavelength light...
比如蓝光
like blue light...
逐步变成波长较长的光 即红光
to gradually become long-wavelength or redder light.
那其实就是我们在星系光谱里
That fundamentally is the cause of the red shift that we see...
看到红移的原因所在
in the spectra of galaxies.
红移又是如何变成测量距离的手段的呢?
How does the red shift turn into a way to measure distance?
那全是因为在1926年的一项惊人发现
It's all because of an astonishing discovery made in 1926...
地点是洛杉矶郊外的威尔逊山天文台
at the Mount Wilson Observatory outside Los Angeles.
登上威尔逊山对我来说一直都非常激动
Being up here on Mount Wilson is always a thrill for me...
因为就是在这个地方
because it was actually right here at this location...
我们对宇宙的看法整个改变了
that our view of the universe entirely changed.
就是在这里 埃德温.哈勃发现了宇宙正在膨胀
It was here that Edwin Hubble found out the universe is expanding...
那是件多不可思议的事情啊
and that was an amazing thing.
出乎他的预料
He wasn't expecting it.
谁都没有想到这种情形 从而改变了一切
Nobody thought that was the case, and it changed everything.
到处都能看到红移
Seeing red shifts everywhere...
哈勃发现宇宙中所有的星系
Hubble found that all of the universe's galaxies...
正彼此拉开距离
were moving away from each other...
我们现在知道了是空间本身的膨胀所造成的
which we now know is caused by the expansion of space itself.
从地球看去
As seen from the Earth...
星系看上去并未离开
a galaxy doesn't look like it's moving away...
但是我们之所以知道 是因为光的红移
but we know that it is because its light is red-shifted.
星系远离的速度不快 会稍许有一点红移
A galaxy moving away at low speed has a slight red shift.
星系远离越快 红移就越厉害
A galaxy moving faster has a larger red shift.
然而哈勃发现那些移动较快的星系
But Hubble found that those faster-moving galaxies...
同时也是较远的
are also farther away.
这就意味着 红移越大
That meant the greater the red shift...
星系就越远
the more distant the galaxy.
通过观察空间膨胀的速度
By seeing how fast space is expanding...
往后推算
and working the math backwards...
宇宙学家已经能够估计出宇宙的年龄
cosmologists have been able to estimate the age of the universe.
将它与光速结合起来
Combine that with light speed...
你就碰到了一个重大的脑筋急转弯
and you have a major brain twister.
宇宙就是这样一个巨大的空间
The universe is such a huge place...
光的旅行时间对我们来说已经非常的重要
that the light travel time really becomes important to us.
我们认为宇宙始于约135亿年前
We believe the universe began about 13 1/2 billion years ago.
这就意味着我们任何方向所能见到最远的距离
That means the farthest in any direction we can look...
就是135亿光年
is 13 1/2 billion light-years.
不会有光的旅行时间大于这个的
There hasn't been enough time for light to travel more than that.
它叫做我们的光视界
It's called our light horizon...
一个往所有方向都是135亿光年的球形
a sphere 13 1/2 billion light-years in all directions...
其中包括了我们所见到的一切
containing everything we can see.
但是那就是脑筋急转弯所在
But that's where the brain twister comes in.
那是不是空间的尽头呢?
Does space end there?
我们没理由认为 我们所能见到的范围
We have no reason to believe that the distance we can see...
就是宇宙的整个大小
is the entire size of the universe.
事实上 它有可能要比这大得多
In fact, it might be much bigger than that.
那只是指 光旅行时间
It's just that, with light travel time...
是我们所能见到的整个范围 那就是我们的视界
that's all we can see. That's our horizon.
细细想想这个谜题吧
So, consider this conundrum.
位于我们视界边缘的一个星系里的天文学家
Astronomers in a galaxy at one edge of our horizon...
是不可能看到我们视界另一头的任何星系的
can't possibly see any galaxies on the other edge of our horizon...
但是他们可以看到另一个方向的
but they can see galaxies...
135亿光年里的星系
13 1/2 billion light-years in the other direction...
而在他们自己视界边缘的天文学家就有可能了
and so can astronomers at the edge of their horizon...
如此以往 或许就是无限远
and on and on, perhaps to infinity.
至于地球上的天文学家 光速将他们困住了
As for astronomers on Earth, light speed has them trapped.
如果我们要问我们光视界之外的事情
lf we ask what is happening beyond our light horizon...
我们就不得不面对这样的事实
we have to face the fact...
就是光速确实是个障碍
that the speed of light really is a barrier.
我们从未见到过我们视界之外的任何东西
We've never seen anything beyond our light horizon.
我们会沉湎于
Can we take comfort in the fact...
这张壮观的照片
that there is so much to see inside our horizon
就是哈勃太空望远镜的超深空
This breathtaking shot is the Hubble Space Telescope's Ultra Deep Field.
这是一个比满月小100倍的空域的大尺度详细照片
It's a massively detailed photo of an area of the sky...
空域的大尺度详细照片
a hundred times smaller than the full Moon...
然而却包含了1万个星系
yet containing 10,000 galaxies...
其中一些光线朝我们传播已经有130亿年了
some whose light has been speeding toward us for 13 billion years.
其背后是宇宙背景辐射
Beyond that is the cosmic background radiation...
距离大爆炸只有40万年
from just 400,000 years after the Big Bang.
在航天局的颜色编码照片里
In NASA's color-coded picture...
辐射的光辉是纯蓝色的
the radiation's glow is pure green...
反映出物质分布十分均匀
representing a distribution of matter so uniform...
其温差不超过五万分之一度
its temperature varies no more than 1/50,000th of a degree.
人类从未碰到过
Nothing in human experience...
这种整齐划一
is even close to this kind of uniformity.
事实上 天文学家认为
In fact, astronomers believe...
宇宙实际上应该存在着很大的差异
the universe should really be very different.
公正地说 宇宙应该是疏密不一的
By rights, the universe should be lumpy.
要是你往这个方向看 往那个方向看
If you look in this direction and you look in that direction...
你应该会看到两个全然不同的物质密度
you should see two entirely different concentrations of matter...
不同的温度
different temperatures...
然而它却是非常均匀的
but it's extremely uniform.
因此 我们碰到了一个难题
Therefore, we have a puzzle.
难题的根源就在于
The puzzle has its roots...
宇宙诞生的大爆炸那一刻
at the universe's birth in the Big Bang.
要是所有的从一开始就相互分开
If everything flew apart from the beginning...
那为何它不应该是整齐划一的呢?
why shouldn't it be uniform?
我们现在知道了没哪一种爆炸
No kind of explosion that we know about...
会导致这种均匀性
leads to that kind of uniformity.
你来想象一个普通的爆炸
If you imagine an ordinary explosion--
原子弹 TNT炸药
an atomic bomb, a piece of TNT--
不会是完全均匀的
it's not really uniform at all.
弹片会飞向那边
There's a piece of shrapnel going off there...
纸片会飞向那边 铁片会飞向那边
piece of paper going off there, an extra piece of iron going off there.
确实是非常不均匀的
It's really very non-uniform.
因此科学家认为宇宙背景辐射
So scientists believe the cosmic background radiation...
就是不应该如此均匀的绿色
just shouldn't be as smooth a green as it is.
我们可以在普通油漆店里找到答案
We can find out why in an ordinary paint store.
我们来把宇宙看作是
Let's consider a universe...
各种颜色的油漆罐
that consists of different colored cans of paint.
在我们的假想油漆宇宙里
In our hypothetical paint universe...
我们拿出一罐黄色的油漆和一罐蓝色的油漆
we have a can of yellow paint and a can of blue paint...
在这个宇宙大爆炸的瞬间
and at the instant of the Big Bang in this universe...
这两罐油漆开始拉开距离
the two cans of paint start expanding apart from each other.
在我们的假想油漆宇宙里 一边呈现出黄色
In our hypothetical paint universe, one side of it would look yellow...
而另一边呈现出蓝色
and the other side would look blue.
但是正如我们所知 宇宙呈现绿色
But as we've learned, the cosmos looks green...
不管是油漆宇宙还是真正的宇宙
whether it's the paint universe or the real thing.
这两种颜色的油漆
The two colors of paint represent the different particles...
代表了初生宇宙的各种粒子
in the infant universe.
要最后形成清一色的绿色
To end up a uniform green...
如宇宙背景辐射那样
like the cosmic background radiation...
它们必须要接触
they had to be touching.
但是当科学家首次计算出大爆炸的速度后
But when scientists first calculated the speed of the Big Bang...
他们得出了结论
they concluded that it blew everything apart...
爆炸的速度要快于光速
faster than the speed of light...
也就是蓝黄分离飞快
meaning blue and yellow were too far apart...
甚至在创世的瞬间 都不会发生任何混合
even at the instant of creation, for any mixing to take place.
看到绿得如此一致的宇宙
Seeing a universe that's so uniformly green...
真是异常的怪异
would be very strange.
就好像拿上一罐黄色的油漆
It would be like taking our can of yellow paint...
倒出来 就已经是绿色的了
pouring it out, and having it be green.
然后拿上一罐蓝色的油漆 倒出来
Then taking a can of blue paint, pouring it out...
同样变成了绿色
and having it be green as well.
那是不可能的事
It's impossible.
这个视界问题的解决可以通过一个理论
This horizon problem can be solved...
也就是我所从事的所谓的暴涨理论
by a theory that I've worked on called inflation...
那是大爆炸的扭曲
which is a twist on the Big Bang.
暴涨是现在广为接受的变异
Inflation is now the widely accepted variation...
它让大爆炸
that makes the Big Bang work...
不受光速的限制
without the limit imposed by the speed of light.
另一个可能发生的情况就是我们的油漆宇宙
Another way this could've happened is that our paint universe...
有可能被炸开就这么远
might have expanded only this far.
两罐油漆已有足够的时间来混合
The two cans of paint have enough time to mix...
变成了均匀的绿色
and become uniformly green...
然后宇宙才经历一个突然的爆发期
before the universe undergoes a sudden period of expansion...
表现得快于光速
that occurs faster than the speed of light.
这就将绿油漆扩散到整个宇宙
This would spread green paint all over the universe.
如果这个理论是正确的
If this theory is right...
暴涨期其实就是我们所见到的那个大爆炸
the period of inflation is really "the" Big Bang that we observe.
而其它爆炸 发生在那之前的
The other bang, that happened before that...
其实就是小爆炸
becomes really a Little Bang.
那只是真正的大爆炸的前兆
It's just a precursor to the real Big Bang.
即使到了现在 宇宙在高速膨胀
Even today, the universe is expanding at high velocity...
星系之间分离速度很快
galaxies speeding away from each other so fast...
它们似乎无视光速
that they seem to violate light speed...
这个终极速度限制
as the ultimate speed limit.
大于光速的空间膨胀
The faster-than-light expansion of space...
甚至还安排了另一个极限 即我们从地球观察
sets yet another limit on what we can see from Earth...
宇宙中的星系不断快速远离我们而去
where the galaxies of the universe continue to rush away from us.
相对离我们较近的星系
The galaxies that are relatively near to us...
你不难看到它们
those that you can see easily...
离开的很快
are moving away pretty fast...
事实上 较远的星系离开得更快
and, indeed, the more distant ones are moving away faster.
然而那些真正很远的星系 事实上
But the ones that are really far away, in fact...
远离的速度超过了光速
are moving away faster than the speed of light.
于是有些星系是你永远见不到的
And then there are the galaxies that you will never see...
因为它们一开始就非常遥远
because they started out so far away...
它们发出的光永远到不了你这里
that the light from them will never reach you...
因为空间的膨胀超过了光速
because the space is expanding faster than the speed of light.
空间本身就违背了规律
Space itself then is the exception to the rule.
其膨胀速度可以超过光速
It can expand faster than the speed of light.
但是其中的一切依然会受到爱因斯坦
But everything inside it remains bound...
及其相对论的约束
by Albert Einstein and his theory of relativity.
爱因斯坦是片警
Albert Einstein is the cop on the block.
你无法突破光的障碍
You cannot break the light barrier.
我们物理学家可以将粒子加速到
We physicists can accelerate particles...
光速的99.9999%
to 99.9999 percent the speed of light...
但是从来没有 也永远不可能突破光速限制
but we have never, ever broken the speed limit.
然而我们无需突破限制
But we don't need to break the limit...
来体验奇异的光速领域
to experience the strange province of light speed.
如果宇宙弯曲和拉伸周围的光速
If the universe bends and stretches around the speed of light...
那么一旦我们开启加速器 开始碰撞时
what happens when we hit the accelerator...
会有何后果呢?
and start to get close?
对我们多数人来说 光似乎很单纯
For most of us, light seems simple and uncomplicated...
品质自然 通过它我们来观察宇宙
a quality of nature by which we see the universe.
但是 在科学审视下
Under the scrutiny of science, however...
它变得很怪异
it becomes strange and bizarre.
光是非常平常的东西 我们每天都要接触
Light is such a common thing in our everyday experience...
但是我们对它确实了解甚少
and yet we have very little understanding of it really.
它非常古怪
It's very weird.
光速是整个宇宙
The speed of light is something...
弯曲周围顺理成章的结果
that the entire universe bends around to accommodate.
我们可以来了解一下
We can begin to understand...
为何宇宙本身会弯曲周围的光速
why the universe bends itself around light speed...
和赛车场上的物理学家克利福德.约翰逊一道
by joining physicist Clifford Johnson at a bicycle track...
来看看网球与光束的一场竞赛
where a tennis ball will compete against a beam of light.
如果我扔出一个普通物体 如这个网球
If I throw an ordinary object like a tennis ball...
只要给它特定的速度 它就会跑出一定的距离
I can throw it at a given speed, it will go a certain distance.
这就是网球的轨迹
This is the path of the tennis ball...
约翰逊将它扔出时 站着没动
as Johnson throws it while he's standing still.
它半道掉在了赛道上
It lands roughly halfway down the track.
接着 他将再次扔球
Next, he'll throw the ball again...
不过这回是骑车
but this time from a moving bike...
结果有所不同
with different results.
如果我以同样的速度扔这个网球
If I throw the tennis ball at that same speed...
由于骑着车子 它将跑得更快些
while riding the bike, it'll go faster...
因为网球的速度加上车子的速度
because it's the speed of the tennis ball...
所以它会跑得更远些
plus the speed of the bike, and so it'll go further.
比较这两投 差异是明显的
Compare the two tosses, and the difference is clear.
在骑车扔球时 球会跑得越来越快
The ball goes faster and farther when thrown from the moving bike.
其意义非凡
It makes perfect sense.
然而现在我们用光来做同样的试验
But now we put light to the same test...
利用自行车前灯来替代网球
using the bike's headlight instead of a tennis ball.
如果我站着不动
If I'm standing stationary...
打开车前灯
and I switch on the headlight of the bike...
车前灯发出光束
that beam of light that comes out of the headlight...
看到的光速
comes out at the speed of light...
不会是其他速度 而是光速
no other speed but the speed of light.
假设光束足够慢
Suppose the beam was slow enough...
让我们能看到它在赛道上移动
for us to actually see its motion down the track.
我们在瞬间之后做上一个标记
We mark its position just a brief moment later.
接着 约翰逊打开骑行中的车前灯
Next, Johnson switches on the headlight at riding speed...
结果出乎意料
and the unexpected happens.
在同样的瞬间
In that same moment of time...
光传播出去的距离和刚才的完全相同
the light travels exactly the same distance as before.
不同于网球
Unlike for the tennis ball...
你不能将车速加上光速
you don't add the speed of the bike...to the speed of the light.
光速还是光速
The speed of light remains the speed of light.
两束光走过的距离相等
The two light beams travel the same distance...
因为光速是恒定的
because light speed is constant...
与光源的运动无关
and independent of the source's motion.
它可以违背直觉 但却是不争的事实
It may fly against intuition, but it is a fact of nature.
宇宙间的每一道光
Every beam of light in the universe...
都以同样的速度穿行于太空
travels at the same speed in empty space...
从不管发出光的恒星 彗星
no matter how fast the star or comet or galaxy...
星系有多快
that emits it is moving.
在科学家于19世纪末发现这个事实后
After scientists discovered this fact at the end of the 19th century...
爱因斯坦为我们进行了数学演算
Albert Einstein did the math for the rest of us...
形成了他的狭义相对论
and developed his special theory of relativity...
光速恒定是其核心
with constant light speed as its center.
了解光速给我们打开了
Understanding the speed of light gave us a window...
了解时空性质的窗口
into understanding the nature of space and time...
我们现在对它已有所了解
as we understand it now.
我们并非生活在一成不变的世界里
We do not live in a rigid world...
那里时间固定 时钟滴答永恒不变
where meter sticks and a clock ticking at regular intervals.
我们是生活在弯曲 弹性的爱因斯坦的世界里
We live in a flexible, stretchy Einstein's world...
时空的相对论世界里
a relativistic world of space and time.
按一般的经验
In common experience...
宇宙在我们看来并没什么弹性
the universe doesn't seem very stretchy to us...
因为相对光速 我们的活动非常的缓慢
because compared to light speed, we are moving very slowly.
但是一旦我们调高速度 情况就会开始变化
But when we crank up the velocity, things begin to change.
随着你越来越接近光速
As you get closer and closer to the speed of light...
千奇百怪的扭曲就会应运而生
all sorts of strange and marvelous distortions take place.
我们说宇宙本身就会弯曲
When we say that the universe kind of bends itself...
而光速是永恒不变的
so that the speed of light is always constant...
这实在是多么惊人的事实啊
it's amazing how literally that's really true.
随着你越来越接近光速
As you move closer and closer to the speed of light...
你的时间
your time appears to slow down...
在旁观者看来是在走慢
to an observer that's just sort of watching you go by.
真令人震惊
That's amazing.
当克利福德.约翰逊在赛道上骑行时
When Clifford Johnson bikes around the track...
必须要比他目前的时速12英里
he needs to be going about 56 million times faster...
快上5600万倍
than his current 12 miles per hour...
才能够接近光速
to get close to light speed.
但愿他能达到
But suppose he could.
想象一下我骑车速度接近光速
Imagine I were riding my bike close to the speed of light.
且不管其可能与否
Never mind whether that's possible or not.
权当真的有这回事
Just imagine that this was happening.
我的时钟会走慢
My clock's running slow...
相对场边拍摄我的摄影师
compared to the cameraman on the ground who's filming me.
假如我跑上一会儿
lf l do that for a while...
我的年龄增长
I'm going to age much more slowly...
要慢于场边的摄影师
than the cameraman who's on the ground.
因此当我下车
So that when I come back from the trip...
回头和摄影师交流时
and come back and talk to the cameraman...
他实际上要比我离开他时老了很多
he's actually much older than when l left him.
如果这听起来像是魔法而不是科学的话
If this sounds like magic instead of science...
这里有一个证明 是我们多数人每天都会碰到的
there is proof in something that many of us experience every day.
爱因斯坦狭义相对论的一个很好的例子
A great example of Einstein's special theory of relativity...
就是事实上 有时钟
and the fact that clocks...
相对运行得比你 比你的生物钟慢一些
that are moving relative to you run more slowly...
那就是静止的 GPS系统
than your own clock, which is at rest, is the GPS system.
全球定位系统
The Global Positioning System...
让我们开车不会迷路
lets us drive our cars without getting lost.
右转
Turn right.
GPS来自一个24颗卫星的网络
GPS begins with a network of 24 satellites...
它们运行在地球上方1.25万英里的地方
orbiting the Earth 12,500 miles above the surface.
随时随地 你车上的装置
At any one time, the device in your car...
至少接收到4颗卫星发出的信号
receives signals from at least four satellites...
通过比较它们的光速穿行时间
and compares their light speed travel times...
来计算出地面上的实际位置
to calculate an accurate location on the ground.
前方500英尺 右拐
Drive 500 feet, then turn right.
整个事情依赖超精准的时钟
The whole thing depends on super accurate clocks.
工程师在设计该系统时
And when the engineers designed the system...
知道卫星的运行速度
they knew the satellites would be orbiting...
将会达到时速7000英里
at nearly 7,000 miles an hour.
这个速度足以放慢它们的时钟
The speed is enough to slow down their clocks...
不足一秒钟
by a tiny fraction of a second.
工程师在系统中考虑了所有的相对论时间差异因素
The engineers have factored all the relativistic time differences...
使其精度叹为观止
into the system, which gives it impressive precision.
如果卫星上的时钟走时
If the clocks in the satellites are running at a different rate...
与地球上的时钟不一致
than the clocks down here on Earth...
你就不会考虑用它了
and you don't take that into account...
你就会接收到你的爱车的错误位置
you will get the wrong answer for where your car is.
前方一英里 目的地往左拐
Drive .1 mile to destination on left.
时间的扭曲只是接近光速旅行
The distortion of time is only one of the strange results...
所产生的怪异结果之一
of traveling close to the speed of light.
在赛道上
On the bike track...
克利福德.约翰逊积蓄在挑战极限
Clifford Johnson continues to push the envelope...
此时空间开始对他和他的自行车施展魔法了
as space begins doing odd things to him and his bicycle.
再次来想象我骑在车上 速度接近光速
Imagine I'm on my bike again, going close to the speed of light.
旁观者实际上会看到 举个例子
An observer looking at me would actually see, for example...
我的车子的长度 沿着我的运动方向
that the length of my bike in the direction of motion I'm moving...
正在缩短
is getting shrunk.
实际上 车子正变得越来越短
Actually, the bike is getting shorter.
这种效果叫做长度收缩
The effect is called length contraction...
结合时间膨胀
and together with time dilation...
这就是静止的旁观者所看到的结果
it is seen by a stationary observer...
发生在看到有人以接近光速旅行时
while looking at someone traveling close to light speed.
不过约翰逊教授确实有机会
But Professor Johnson does get his own chance...
一睹光速所带来的奇怪结果
to witness light speed's weird effects.
由于他的速度接近光速
As his velocity closes in on light speed...
他看到的世界发生了巨大的改变
his view of the world changes drastically.
我接近光速前行
What I'm seeing as I move close...
所看到的是
to the speed of light straight ahead...
我面前的模样相对日常生活里的情形
is that the shapes in front of me...
正变得异常的扭曲变形
are getting quite distorted as compared to everyday life.
一切都被扭曲成有点像管道
Everything is being twisted into a sort of tunnel shape...
颜色也被扭曲成五颜六色
and the colors are getting distorted in various ways.
颜色的改变来自多普勒效应
The color changes come from the Doppler effect...
形状的扭曲
and the shape distortions...
来自所谓的象差现象
from a phenomenon known as aberration.
扭曲有点类似于
The distortion is somewhat similar to what you would see...
你在暴雨中开车所见到的情形
if you were driving through a rainstorm.
假如你静止不动
If you were stationary...
你就会看到雨滴笔直降下
you would just see the rain coming straight down...
是你从窗户看出去的情形
if you looked out of the side of the window.
但是 要是你在雨中穿行
Whereas, if you were moving through the storm...
你就会看到雨滴似乎斜着打向你
you would see that the rain appears to be slanting towards you...
那是由于你运动的缘故
as a result of your motion.
那是你由于你所看到的扭曲的缘故
And that's at the basis of that warping effect that you get...
此时你接近光速
as you're moving near the speed of light...
奔向你面前的物体
towards objects in front of you.
事实上 我们不必
In reality, we don't have to travel near the speed of light...
以接近光速运动来
to experience the distortions...
体验穿行时空所造成的扭曲
caused by motion through time and space.
它们每时每刻都在与我们为伴
They are with us every minute of the day.
极限光速
All of the distortions that happen...
所产生的所有变形
as a result of a finite speed of light...
还是会体现在日常中
still happen on an everyday basis...
甚至我们的日常生活中
even in our everyday life...
但是这种影响微乎其微 我们难以觉察而已
but the effects are so tiny that we can't perceive them.
不过 光速在低速世界里
Still, light speed has its other quirks...
也有其怪癖之处
in the slow-moving world...
我们感觉良好的怪癖
quirks we perceive very well.
光速可以是个常数
The speed of light may be a constant...
但只是在真空中如此
but only in the vacuum of space.
当光穿过玻璃或液体之类的物体时
When light moves through things like glass or fluids...
会明显减速
it slows down appreciably.
要不这样 望远镜之类的东西
lf it didn't, things like telescopes...
人眼要看清是简直不可能的
and human vision would be impossible.
但要是光速很低 乃至光速为零时
But what would happen if light slowed down much more...
又当如何呢?
if the speed of light were zero?
光速 每秒18.6万英里
Light speed is 186,000 miles per second.
它是宇宙的常数 但可望不可及
It is a universal constant, but a constant with a catch.
这个速度只有在真空中
It travels at that speed only in a vacuum.
光会改变其速度
Light changes its speed...
一旦穿越不同的介质
when it travels through different media.
它穿越水时 速度很慢
It travels more slowly through water.
那就是为什么你在水下可以看到折射和弯曲
That's why you see refraction and bending...
以及波光粼粼的原因所在
and rippling of light when you're underwater.
我们知道它的结局会截然不同
Life as we know it would be very different...
假如光在穿越不同的介质时
if light didn't propagate at different speeds...
传播的速度不一样的话
through different materials.
比如 我们就会看不到它
For example, we wouldn't be able to see.
同样 我们的眼睛就无法工作
Our eyes wouldn't work the same way.
在某个宇宙中 光以同样的速度
In a universe where light moved at the same speed...
穿越所有的介质
through all materials...
我们就会对周围的世界很少知晓
we would know little of the world around us...
就只能看到模糊的斑点 非明则暗
seeing only vague blobs of dark and light.
那是因为我们眼睛依靠生物透镜
That's because our eyes depend on biological lenses...
将图像聚焦到我们的视网膜
to focus images on our retinas.
犹如玻璃镜头
Just like lenses made of glass...
其原理在于光线穿透时会减缓速度
they work because light slows down as it passes through them.
那又是何故呢?
Now why is that?
因为光会被玻璃的原子所吸收
Because light is absorbed by the atoms of glass...
稍后会再次发射出来 因此存在着一个延迟因素
and then they re-radiate it later, so there's a delay factor.
光轰击原子 原子震荡
Light hits an atom, the atom vibrates...
然后将光打包发送出去
and then sends a light package off.
所以存在着延迟因素
So there's a delay factor.
延迟因素也会造成光的弯曲
The delay factor also causes light to bend...
只要它轰击被做成透镜的玻璃
when it hits glass shaped into a lens.
只要弯曲到适当的程度
Bent in just the right way...
光就会被聚焦 聚集和放大
light can be focused, collected, and magnified.
对于天文学家研究宇宙来说
For astronomers studying the universe...
没有什么比这更重要的了
nothing could be more important.
多亏了光在穿透玻璃时速度减缓
Thank goodness light slows down when it goes through glass...
在于我们要使用望远镜的缘故
because that's the reason why we have telescopes.
我们使用望远镜的原因
The reason why we have telescopes...
就在于光穿越玻璃时会弯曲
is because light bends going through glass...
我们可以将大量的光集中到一点
and we can concentrate large amounts of light to a single point...
这样就能够让我们一睹
and then that gives us the ability...
宇宙本身的奇迹了
to see the marvels in the universe itself.
光穿越望远镜的玻璃镜头
Light travels through the glass lenses of telescopes...
速度约每秒12.4万英里
at about 124,000 miles per second...
是其真空中的速度的三分之二
two-thirds of its speed through a vacuum.
不过有些科学家正在寻求
But some scientists are looking at making use of light...
利用速度慢得多的光
at far slower speeds.
在哈佛大学的实验室里
At her lab on the campus of Harvard University...
莉娜.豪博士已经将光速降到了极致
Dr. Lene Hau has taken slow light...
光速降到了零
to the extreme by reducing light speed to zero.
光的速度 当然非常的高
The speed of light, of course, is incredibly high.
我说的是 没有什么比光跑得更快的了
I mean, nothing goes faster than light...
要知道 一般是每秒18.6万英里
and, you know, the usual 186,000 miles per second.
我们会想 哎 太高了吧
And we kind of thought, gee, that's awfully high.
让我们来尝试对它干点什么吧
Let's try to do something about it.
可以安装探测器吗?
Can we have the detector right there?
豪和她的团队在做他们的实验
Hau and her team conducted their experiments...
综合实验室里装满了激光器 镜面
in a complex laboratory filled with lasers, mirrors...
棱镜和各种试验设备
prisms, and other exotic gear.
这是物理学的一个开创性的分支
It is a branch of physics where few have dared to tread.
如果你能够着手将东西变得如此戏剧性
If you can start to change things so dramatically...
把这个极大的光速
as taking this enormous light speed...
降低到自行车的速度
and then bring it down to bicycle speed...
你就进入了一个崭新的自然领域了
then you're in a completely new regime of nature.
你现在已经涉足新的领域
You're able to now start to probe areas...
以前从没有人涉足的自然领域
regions of nature where nobody has ever been there before.
制动已经施加给了光速 在豪的实验室里
The brakes are put on light speed inside Hau's lab...
通过将激光聚焦到两个微小的钠气体云团
by focusing lasers on two microscopic clouds of sodium gas...
云团被冷却到绝对零度几十亿分之一度
chilled to a few billionths of a degree above absolute zero.
一束受控的激光轰击这两个云团
A control laser hitting the two clouds...
使它们进行反应
sets them up for action.
这样快速光脉冲射击第一个云团
Then a quick light pulse shoots into the first cloud...
被挤压进气体
where it is squeezed into the gas...
速度被减缓到时速只有几英里
and slowed to just a few miles per hour.
光脉冲从一开始在自由空间中长约1公里
The light pulse goes from being about one kilometer long in free space.
它在进入原子云后 像手风琴那样被压缩了
It compresses like a concertina as it enters the atom cloud...
最后变成了只有0.02毫米长
and ends up being only 0.02 millimeter in size.
还不到头发的一半
That's less than half the thickness of a hair...
确实非常小
so really small.
小到光脉冲实际上
And it's so small that the light pulse...
最后整个装进气体云里了
actually ends up fitting totally inside the atom cloud.
据豪说 钠气体云里的光原子痕迹
Hau says the atomic imprint of light in the sodium cloud...
是原始光脉冲原子
is a perfect copy embedded in atoms...
嵌入后的完美副本
of the original light pulse.
于是它就被停留在了
It can then be stopped in free space...
两团云团之间的自由空间里了
between the two clouds before moving on.
在它进入第二个云团后
When it enters the second cloud...
另一束受控激光将其扩展到
another shot of the control laser...
最初的尺度和形状
expands it to its original size, shape...
速度达到了每秒18.6万英里
and speed of 186,000 miles per second.
这类似于某些科幻小说中的输送机
It is comparable in some ways to a science fiction transporter...
将人和物送入太空
that sends people or objects through space.
因此在这些实验中 我们所做的就是
So in these experiments what we really do is...
将光脉冲停止和扑灭在了空间的某个地方
we stop and extinguish a light pulse in one part of space...
然后又在空间的另一个地方将其恢复
and revive it in a completely different part of space...
沿着原来的路径传播
and send it back on its way.
由于光可以携带信息
Since light can carry information...
因此这个开拓性的科技直指
this super-advanced technology points the way...
未来的光基计算机
to futuristic light-based computers...
将抛开电线和电子芯片
that bypass wires and electronic chips.
信息直接从光读取
Information read directly from light...
可能会比我们今天所有的一切都来得
may be faster, more compact, and more secure...
更快 更紧凑 更安全
than anything we have today.
但是科学家和梦想家最大的远景
But the greatest vision of scientists and dreamers...
就是找到光速范围的另外一头
is to be found at the other end of the light speed spectrum.
我们依然面对着光速如坚不可摧的城墙
We still face the speed of light as an impenetrable wall...
爱因斯坦已告诉我们 其速度永远不可逾越
a speed that Dr. Einstein told us could never be exceeded.
但是历史上 不可能变为可能已经比比皆是
Yet history is packed with impossibles that have become realities.
比如 我们有没有可能进入太空
Will we ever, for instance, be able to reach the stars...
飞船超过光速呢?
in ships that go faster than the speed of light?
要是可以 又在何时?
If so, when?
2008年4月 世界著名物理学家斯蒂芬.霍金
In April 2008, world-famous physicist Stephen Hawking...
呼吁人类殖民太空
called on the human race to colonize space...
将星际旅行作为长期目标
and make interstellar travel a long-term aim.
拓展太空
Spreading out into space...
将彻底改变人类的未来
will completely change the future of the human race...
乃至决定我们未来的一切
and maybe determine whether we have any future at all.
恒星太远了 使得星际旅行不切实际
The stars are so far away that interstellar travel is impractical...
除非我们可以超过光速
unless we can go faster than light speed...
但那是一个障碍
but that's an obstacle.
爱因斯坦的相对论
Einstein's theory of relativity...
告诉我们 飞船的质量
tells us that a spaceship's mass...
在接近光速时会趋于无穷大
approaches infinity as it nears the speed of light.
因而 你试图跑得越来越快的话
So as you try to go to faster and faster and faster...
你其实就需要
you actually get to a point...
用上越来越多的能量
where it takes more and more energy...
直到用上无穷大的能量
until it's an infinite amount of energy...
来得到光速
to go to speed of light.
这是不可能做到的
That's impossible.
这就意味着以光速旅行同样是办不到的
It means that travel at light speed is also impossible.
是这么回事吗?
Or is it?
马克.米利斯为数不多的科学家之一
Marc Millis is one of a handful of scientists...
他对这个问题并不准备认输
who isn't ready to throw in the towel on the subject.
作为航天局一名专业的推进物理学家
A NASA propulsion physicist by profession...
他喜欢在业余时间建造飞船模型
he likes to build models of starships in his spare time...
深蕴所有提及星际旅行的
and is well aware of the giggle factor...
科幻小说的咯咯因子
in any talk outside science fiction of star travel.
咯咯因子实际上是健康反应
The giggle factor is actually a healthy response.
它有助于怀疑论者对话题提出深层次的问题
It helps provide skepticism to the topic to ask deep questions...
以确保我们的进程准确无误
to make sure that we're proceeding correctly.
作为航天局已尘封的突破推进项目的昔日领导
Once head of NASA's mothballed Breakthrough Propulsion Project...
米利斯在编辑一本书
Millis is editor of a book...
书中收集了当前有关这个课题的重要研究成果
that has collected the serious current research on the subject.
说起光速问题
When it comes just to the light speed issue...
有大约30多位物理学家
there's about three dozen physicists...
撰写了文章 有人怀疑
who've written articles, some skeptical...
有人对这个课题提出了新的方法
some suggesting new methods on the topic.
没有人说在短时间内
No one is saying that anytime soon...
我们会有能力前往星际
we'll be able to have warp drive to the stars.
但是站在数百乃至千年的角度
But on a scale of centuries to millennia...
就不能排除这种可能性了
it can't be ruled out.
几乎所有的物理学家都同意
Virtually all physicists agree...
以超越光速来穿行太空
it's impossible to travel through space...
是不可能的
at faster than light speed.
但是或许有一个办法来作弊
But there may be a way to cheat...
就是改变空间而不是穿行空间
by altering space instead of traveling through it.
不管相信与否 甚至航天局的科学家都在研究那种可能性
Believe it or not, even NASA scientists are studying the possibility...
那就是或许我们可以折叠空间 在空间打个窟窿
that perhaps we can fold space, punch a hole in space...
打造个地铁系统来穿越时空
make a subway system through space and time.
其背后的基本概念就是利用虫洞
That's the basic idea behind using wormholes...
来扭曲其周围的空间
to actually twist space around on itself...
找到穿越宇宙的捷径
and take a shortcut through the universe.
虫洞机器会是什么模样呢?
What would a wormhole machine look like?
大概要调用规模庞大的设备
Probably huge in scale with equipment staged...
也许要立足于大量的小行星
perhaps on a massive number of asteroids...
来安排一个巨大的范围
arranged in a gigantic sphere.
需要一个巨大的激光阵
It would require an enormous battery of laser beams...
集中巨大的能量于一点
that concentrate tremendous energy to a single point.
你必须达到极高的温度
You have to attain fantastic temperatures...
我们宇宙中可能达到的最高能量
the highest energy attainable in our universe...
来打开一个窟窿 一个泡泡
in order to open up a hole, a bubble...
一个门户 或许就可以通往另一个宇宙了
a gateway perhaps to another universe.
另一个蒙骗空间之道
Another way of tricking space...
让我们超越光速穿行太空 就是曲相推进
into letting us travel faster than light is the warp drive.
米格尔.阿尔库维雷在1994年
Miguel Alcubierre was the first one...
首次提出了曲相推进
to write about the warp drive in 1994.
阿尔库维雷 墨西哥物理学家解决的数学
Alcubierre, a Mexican physicist, worked out the math for a starship...
可以通过扭曲时空本身来推进飞船
propelled by warping space-time itself.
飞船背后 时空是扩大的
Behind the ship, space-time is expanded.
而在飞船前面 时空是压缩的
In front of the ship, space-time contracts.
两者之间 飞船如冲浪那样飞行
In between, the ship rides like a surfer.
飞船本身置身于一个泡泡中
The ship itself sits inside a bubble...
其周围的空间推着它超过了光速
and the space around it pushes it faster than light.
一个成功的曲相推进 要是它真的可能
A successful warp drive, if it is possible at all...
或许就在几百年之后
is probably centuries away.
但是在瑞士 大型强子对撞机的物理学家们
But in Switzerland, physicists at the Large Hadron Collider...
有可能现在就已经找到了正确的方向
may be headed in the right direction right now.
大型强子对撞机是一种原子加速器
Now, the Large Hadron Collider is an atom smasher.
是粒子对撞机
It's a particle collider.
不过它会产生足够高的能量
But it's going to get to high enough energies...
让时空扭曲和弯曲
that space and time will actually warp and bend.
我们实际上是在实验室里练习如何来弯曲空间
We're actually practicing how to bend space in the laboratory.
这是朝着曲相推进的幼稚的第一步
It's the first baby step toward a warp drive.
基于我们现在所掌握的物理学
With the physics we now know...
我们不会在可预见的将来
we won't travel faster than light speed...
超越光速
in the foreseeable future.
那并不意味着我们不该去尝试
That doesn't mean we shouldn't try.
即使光速旅行有可能的结果是做不到的
Even though light speed travel might turn out to be impossible...
未经努力就放弃了 其本身就是放弃
to give up without trying is just giving up.
离开了航天局的工作
Outside his work at NASA...
米利斯创办了非盈利的T 0基金
Millis has founded the nonprofit Tau Zero Foundation...
来鼓励对星际旅行的深入研究
to encourage serious research on star travel.
尽管只有少数科学家在积极推进这个概念
Although few scientists are pursuing the idea actively...
多数人还是同意这个努力还是有价值的
many agree it's worth at least the effort.
了解我们的宇宙
Understanding our universe...
是人类作为一个智能物种
is one of the most basic needs human beings have...
最基本的需求之一
as an intelligent species.
因此我们所追求的科技和物理学难道该不该
So should we pursue technologies or physics...
让我们有朝一日速度超过光速呢?
that might allow us someday to travel faster than light?
完全应该
Absolutely.
因为我们永远不知道这会将我们带向何处
Because we never know where this might take us.
即使我们有可能永远都发现不了
Even though we might never discover a way...
超越光速之道
to travel faster than light...
但是我们有可能发现一大堆其它非常有用的东西
we might discover a whole bunch of other very useful things.
倘若科学
And what if science ultimately proves...
最终证明光速不可逾越
the light speed barrier is unbreakable...
星际旅行难道就行不通了吗?
and star travel is impossible?
它将对地球这个星际飞船提出全新的远景
It would put a whole new perspective on spaceship Earth...
迫使我们作为其乘客
forcing us to use our technology to treat it well...
利用我们的科技
as we remain its passengers...
一如既往地善待它 以及我们的宇宙
on our continuing journey through the universe.